Onondaga County Community College Presidents' Collection
Onondaga Community College
Presidents' Office Collection
1962 - 2018
Onondaga Community College
4585 W Seneca Turnpike Syracuse, NY 13215
This collection is open to researchers without restriction.
This collection encompasses letters, memos, and documents from the Office of the President of Onondaga Community College.
Onondaga Community College; Almstead, Francis; Mackenzie, Ransom; Dmohowski, George; Klein, Philip G; Burtis, Howard; Mayor’s Commission for Youth, Inc. (Syracuse, N.Y.); College administrators; Campus planning; Association of American Colleges and Universities; Rapp, Marvin A.
The collection consists of archival material of the people who have served as President of Onondaga Community College, from the founding of the College to the present day. The collection contains memorandums, letters, documents, etc.
- Office of Dr. Francis Almstead (February 1962 - December 1967), 1962 - 1967; Archival material related to the Presidency of Dr. Francis Almstead. Almstead was the first President of Onondaga Community College. He was President from February 1962 to December 1965. Almstead obtained a B.S. and M.S. from St. Lawrence University. Previous positions before becoming OCC President include: science teacher Coeymans, Clinton and Bellmore (all NY) High Schools; NYS Education Dept. Supervisor of Secondary Education; U.S. Navy 1942 to 1946; U.S. Office of Education 1946; SUNY Executive Dean for Institutes and Community Colleges, developed statewide ETV network for NYS Education Dept. After OCC, Mr. Almstead became Director of Technical Services and Research at St. Lawrence University 1966 to 1981. He died December 13, 1985, in Schenectady, NY. The Collection contains memos and correspondence relating to Almstead's time as President of Onondaga Community College.
  - Memorandum and Minutes - Board of Trustees and Committees, 1962 - 1965; Typed memos to members of the Board of Trustees and various Committees. (Box-folder PRE1 - 1)
    - Memo to Mr. Faulkner on Academic Standards, October 24, 1962; One paragraph, typed memo to Mr. Faulkner regarding on academic standards for evaluating students.
    - Memo to Glenn Williams on Library, December 18, 1962; One paragraph, typed memo regarding the need for a library for the College.
    - Memo to Ransom McKenzie on Items for Board Meeting, July 28, 1965; 2 paged, typed memo to Ransom McKenzie regarding items for a Board Meeting. Notes that 905 students have made a deposit for enrollment. Mentions four attachments but attachments are not included.
    - Minutes of Board of Trustees, 1965
  - Correspondence with Other Colleges, 1962 - 1965; Correspondence to other Community Colleges. (Box-folder PRE1 - 2, PRE2A)
    - Memo from Jane B. Donegan on visit to Broome Technical Community College, November 1, 1962; Typed 2 page memo from Jane B. Donegan to President Almstead regarding a visit in October, 1962 to Broome Technical Community College. Information was gathered from Lloyd W. Hartmann, Chairman of the Division of General Studies, and Jane Foley, Chief Librarian.
    - Letter to Cecil Tyrrel, President of Broome Technical Community College regarding Need for Chemistry Instructor, October 2, 1963; Typed letter to Cecil C. Tyrrel, President of Broome Technical Community College, asking if he knows anyone who would be willing to be a chemistry technician at OCC for a modest salary.
    - Letter to William L. Perry, President of Corning Community College regarding Basketball Season, November 6, 1962; Typed letter to William L. Perry, President of Corning Community College, inquiring if the Corning Community College Men's Basketball team would be able to play home and home against OCC for the upcoming season. Paul N. Seymour mentioned as coach of the OCC Men's Basketball team.
    - Letter to William L. Perry, President of Corning Community College regarding President's Workshop, July 28, 1964; Typed letter to William Perry, President of Corning Community College regarding a "President's Workshop." Asks Perry for comments and suggestions regarding the topic they are both working on, related to professional staff.
    - Letter to Dr. James F. Hall, President of Dutchess Community College regarding Invitation, October 21, 1964; Typed letter to Dr. James F. Hall, President of Dutchess Community College, declining to attend a reception for William B. Connor.
    - Letter from Robert McKinney, Executive Dean of Dutchess Community College, to President Almstead regarding Teacher Load Profile Forms, November 23, 1964; Typed letter from Robert McKinney, Executive Dean of Dutchess Community College, regarding the completion of Teacher Load Profile forms.
    - Letter from Robert McKinney, Executive Dean of Dutchess Community College regarding Questionnaire on Courses and Programs, December 7, 1964; Typed letter from Robert McKinney, Executive Dean of Dutchess Community College asking Almstead to complete a questionnaire regarding programs and courses offered at OCC.
    - Letter from Laurence E. Spring, President of Erie County Technical Institute Regarding Librarian, May 1, 1962; Typed letter from Laurence E. Spring, President of Erie County Technical Institute inquiring if there was an open position for a Head Librarian at OCC. A Librarian, Janice Gallinger, at Erie County Technical has expressed interest in a Head Librarian position.
    - Letter to Laurence E. Spring, President of Erie County Technical Institute, regarding Head Librarian Position, May 14, 1962; Typed letter in response to Spring's letter about Janice Gallinger, a librarian interested in the Head Librarian position at OCC. Almstead responds that he had already had another candidate in mind for the position.
    - Letter to Laurence E. Spring, President of Erie County Technical Institute regarding Basketball Schedule, November 6, 1962; Typed letter to Laurence E. Spring inquiring if the Erie County Technical Institute Men's Basketball team could arrange a home and home series with the newly formed OCC Men's Basketball team.
    - Letter to Laurence Spring, President of Erie County Technical Institute regarding Jim Shenton, November 23, 1962; Typed letter, with handwriting, to Laurence Spring, President of Erie County Technical Institute, asking for the availability of Jim Shenton to serve as a consultant.
    - Letter from Ernest Notar, Dean of Erie County Technical Institute, regarding George Bidwell, December 17, 1962; Typed Letter from Ernest Notar, Dean of Erie County Technical Institute, asking Almstead if George Bidwell was a good candidate to operate Erie County Technical Institute's closed circuit TV.
    - Letter to Ernest Notar, Dean of Erie County Technical Institute, regarding George Bidwell, December 19, 1962; Typed Letter to Ernest Notar, Dean of Erie County Technical Institute, affirming that George Bidwell is a good candidate for operating closed circuit television.
    - Letter from Ernest Notar, Dean of Erie County Technical Institute regarding Help in Starting New College, March 18, 1963; Typed letter from Ernest Notar, Dean of Erie County Technical Institute, stating he has accepted a position as President of the newly formed Niagara County Community College. Asks for literature, application forms, brochures, etc. that Almstead used in forming OCC.
    - Letter to Ernest Notar regarding appointment as Niagara County Community College President, March 21, 1963; Typed letter to Ernest Notar congratulating him on his appointment to President of Niagara County Community College.
    - Letter from James Shenton regarding contract with Faculty Student Association, May 21, 1965; Typed letter, with handwriting, from Jim Shenton, Acting President of Erie County Technical Institute, asking for a copy of OCC's contract with the Faculty Student Association.
    - Letter to James Shenton in response to contract question, May 24, 1965; Typed letter informing James Shenton, Acting President of Erie County Technical Institute, that the Board of Trustees does not have a contract with the Faculty-Student Association.
    - Letter from Norman H. Foote, Chairman, Division of Agriculture & Ornamental Horticulture at Agricultural and Technical Institute at Farmingdale, regarding Appointment at OCC, June 6, 1962; Typed letter from Norman H. Foote, Chairman, Division of Agriculture & Ornamental Horticulture at Agricultural and Technical Institute at Farmingdale, congratulating Almstead on becoming President of OCC.
    - Letter to Norman H. Foote in response to Congratulation Letter, June 7, 1962; Typed letter to Norman H. Foote, thanking him for sending a letter congratulating him on his appointment as President of OCC.
    - Letter to Dean B. Frank Fuller Jr., Fashion Institute of Technology regarding By-laws, May 12, 1965; Typed letter to Dean B. Frank Fuller Jr., Fashion Institute of Technology, asking for a copy of the Fashion Institute of Technology's by-laws for help in drafting a set of by-laws at OCC.
    - Invitation and Declination to Harpur College (Binghamton University) Commencement, May 22, 1963; Invitation to Harpur College (now Harpur College of Arts and Sciences at Binghamton University) Commencement Exercises, along with typed response from Almstead, declaring he was unable to attend.
    - Letter from Nicholas Alexander, Dean of Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary, regarding invitation to Commencement, May 24, 1965; Typed letter from Nicholas Alexander, Dean of Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary in Jordanville, NY, inviting Almstead and his wife to Holy Trinity's Commencement.
    - Letter to Nicholas Alexander, Dean of Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary, declining invitation to Commencement, May 28, 1965; Typed letter to Nicholas Alexander, Dean of Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary, declining invitation to Holy Trinity's Commencement due to it being on the same day as OCC's Commencement.
    - Letter to Otto V. Guenther, President of Hudson Valley Community College, regarding Meeting in Syracuse, December 28, 1962; Typed letter to Otto V. Guenther, President of Hudson Valley Community College, confirming date for a meeting at Midtown Plaza.
    - Letter from Otto V. Guenther, President of Hudson Valley Community College, regarding meeting in Syracuse, January 7, 1963; Typed letter from Otto V. Guenther, President of Hudson Valley Community College, confirming he will attend meeting in Syracuse.
    - Letter to Otto V. Guenther, President of Hudson Valley Community College, regarding filling Chemistry Technician Position, October 2, 1963; Typed letter to Otto V. Guenther, President of Hudson Valley Community College, inquiring if Guenther knew of anyone interested in working as an assistant instructor in Chemistry at OCC.
    - Letter from Otto V. Guenther, President of Hudson Valley Community College, regarding Chemistry Technician Position at OCC, October 3, 1963; Typed letter from Letter from Otto V. Guenther, President of Hudson Valley Community College, informing Almstead that he would keep the position in mind when the current senior class graduates.
    - Letter from Francis J. Kramer, Hudson Valley Community College, regarding Faculty Personnel Policy Handbook, October 19, 1965; Typed letter from Francis J. Kramer, Chairman of the Handbook Revision Committee at Hudson Valley Community College, asking for a copy of OCC's faculty personnel policy handbook.
    - Letter to Albert W. Baisler, President of Jamestown Community College, regarding basketball schedule, November 6, 1962; Typed letter to Albert W. Baisler, President of Jamestown Community College, regarding scheduling a home and home game schedule with the newly formed OCC Men's Basketball team.
    - Letter from E.T. Stapleford, Assistant Professor at Jamestown Community College, regarding Salary Increments, October 4, 1963; Letter from E.T. Stapleford, Assistant Professor of Mathematics at Jamestown Community College, asking how OCC determines salary increments for faculty members.
    - Letter to E.T. Stapleford, Assistant Professor at Jamestown Community College regarding Salary Increment Question, October 7, 1963; Typed letter to E.T. Stapleford, Assistant Professor at Jamestown Community College replying to Stapleford's letter about salary policies.
    - Letter from Albert W. Baisler, President of Jamestown Community College, regarding Public Relations Materials, May 19, 1964; Typed letter from Albert W. Baisler, President of Jamestown Community College, asking Almstead to send a packet of OCC's public relations materials for a display.
    - Letter to Albert W. Baisler, President of Jamestown Community College, regarding Public Relations Materials, May 28, 1964; Typed letter to Albert W. Baisler, President of Jamestown Community College, thanking hom for the reminder about sending public relations materials.
    - Letter from Albert W. Baisler, President of Jamestown Community College regarding California Junior College Film, September 22, 1964; Typed letter from Albert W. Baisler, President of Jamestown Community College about a film he received about junior colleges produced by the State of California.
    - Letter from Albert W. Baisler, President of Jamestown Community College, regarding Egman Studios, 1964; Typed letter from Albert W. Baisler, President of Jamestown Community College, regarding Egman Studios.
    - Letter to Albert W. Baisler, President of Jamestown Community College, regarding visit to OCC, December 10, 1964; Typed letter to Albert W. Baisler, President of Jamestown Community College, thanking him for his suggestions for improving OCC during his visit to the College.
    - Letter to Dr. James E. McVean, President of Jefferson Community College, regarding Jefferson Community College Inaguration, November 5, 1963; Typed letter to Dr. James E. McVean congratulating him on Jefferson Community College's Inauguration exercises.
    - Letter to Arnold Shapiro, President of Board of Trustees of Jefferson Community College, regarding Inauguration, November 19, 1963; Typed letter to Arnold Shapiro, President of Board of Trustees of Jefferson Community College, thanking him for inviting him and his wife to lunch for President McVean's Inauguration.
    - Letter to Albert V. Payne, President of Mohawk Valley Technical Institute, regarding Meeting, December 28, 1962; Typed letter to Albert V. Payne, President of Mohawk Valley Technical Institute, confirming time and date of meeting at Midtown Plaza.
    - Letter to Seymour Eskow, Dean of Mohawk Valley Technical Institute, regarding Appointment as President of Rockland Community College, May 20, 1963; Typed letter to Seymour Eskow, Dean of Mohawk Valley Technical Institute, congratulating him on his appointment as President of Rockland Community College.
    - Letter of Thanks from Seymour Eskow, Dean of Mohawk Valley Technical Institute, May 23, 1963; Typed letter thanking Almstead for congratulating Eskow on his appointment as President to Rockland Community College.
    - Letter to LeRoy V. Good, President of Monroe Community College, regarding Basketball Season Schedule, November 6, 1962; Typed letter to LeRoy V. Good, President of Monroe Community College, asking if it was possible to schedule home and home games against the newly-formed OCC men's basketball team.
    - Letter to Royson N. Whipple, Director of Agricultural and Technical Institute at Morrisville regarding Basketball Season Schedule, November 6, 1962; Typed letter to Royson N. Whipple, Director of Agricultural and Technical Institute at Morrisville, asking if it were possible to schedule home and home games with the newly formed OCC men's basketball team.
    - Letter to Royson N. Whipple, President of Agricultural and Technical Institute at Morrisville, regarding Invitation, February 19, 1963; Typed letter to Royson N. Whipple, President of Agricultural and Technical Institute at Morrisville, accepting invitation to dinner.
    - Letter from Royson N. Whipple, President of Agricultural and Technical Institute at Morrisville, inviting Almstead to Dinner and Concert, February 12, 1963; Typed letter from Royson N. Whipple, President of Agricultural and Technical Institute at Morrisville, inviting Almstead and his wife to dinner and a concert of Billy Butterfield and his orchestra.
    - Letter to Royson N. Whipple, President of Agricultural and Technical Institute at Morrisville, regarding trip from Morrisville, March 15, 1963; Typed letter to Royson N. Whipple, President of Agricultural and Technical Institute at Morrisville, telling Whipple his trip from Morrisville to Syracuse was uneventful and that he enjoyed the concert.
    - Letter to Royson N. Whipple, President of Agricultural and Technical Institute at Morrisville, regarding visit to OCC, December 10, 1964; Typed letter to Royson N. Whipple, President of Agricultural and Technical Institute at Morrisville, thanking him for this suggestions for improving Onondaga Community College during his visit to the campus.
    - Letter from Royson N. Whipple, President of Agricultural and Technical Institute at Morrisville, regarding Check, April 6, 1965
    - Letter from Murray H. Block, Acting President of New York City Community College, regarding faculty rank, February 26, 1963; Typed letter from Murray H. Block, Acting President of New York City Community College, asking what faculty can become "full" professors.
    - Letter to Murray H. Block, Acting President of New York City Community College, regarding Faculty Rank, March 14, 1964; Typed letter to, Murray H. Block, Acting President of New York City Community College, telling Block that OCC places no restrictions on the full professor rank and that the College was considering rotating department chairmen.
    - Letter to Dr. Murray H. Block, Acting President of New York City Community College, regarding copy of Concord, July 3, 1964; Typed letter to Dr. Murray H. Block, Acting President of New York City Community College, thanking him for the copy of Concord, a publication from faculty at NYC Community College.
    - Letter from Murray H. Block, Acting President of New York City Community College, regarding Concord publication, July 9, 1964; Typed letter from Murray H. Block, Acting President of New York City Community College, writing that he is giving Almstead a copy of a NYC Community College faculty publication called, "Concord."
    - Letter form Allan Goodwin, of Orange County Community College, regarding Faculty Contract, December 10, 1965; Typed letter from Allan Goodwin, Chairman of the Professional Problems Committee of the Faculty Association of Orange County Community College, asking for a copy of your standard faculty contract form and statement of academic freedom, tenure, and sabbatical policy.
    - Letter from J. Butler Sullivan, Assistant Director of Admissions at SUNY Potsdam, regarding Student Transfers to Four-Year Colleges, January 20, 1966; Typed letter from J. Butler Sullivan, Assistant Director of Admissions at SUNY Potsdam, regarding a meeting on problems with student transfers from two-year colleges to four-year colleges. Includes summary of guidelines from the meeting held in New York City.
    - Letter from J.B. Aidala, Department of Electrical Engineering at Queensborough Community College, regarding Brochure, August 25, 1965; Typed letter from Professor J.B. Aidala, Chairman of the Dept. of Electrical Engineering at Queensborough Community College, saying he is enclosing a copy of the his department's new brochure. Brochure not with letter. Includes copy form sheets.
    - Letter from Joseph D. Santora, Department of Physical Education at Queensborough Community College, regarding State Conference, January 19, 1965; Typed letter from Joseph D. Santora, Chairman of the Department of Physical Education at Queensborough Community College, thanking Almstead for attending the Junior College Section of a state conference in Syracuse.
    - Letter from Seymour Eskow, President of Rockland Community College, regarding Faculty Rank, October 23, 1963; Typed letter from Seymour Eskow, President of Rockland Community College, asking how OCC determines faculty rank and salary ranges. Includes survey filled out by Glenn WIlliams, OCC Director of Information, that gives information on number of OCC faculty with type of degree and salary information.
    - Letter from Seymour Eskow, President of Rockland Community College, regarding Gift to Paul Orvis, July 1, 1965; Typed letter from Seymour Eskow, President of Rockland Community College, asking for $5 to go towards a gift for Paul Orvis.
    - Letter to Dr. Walter L. Willig, President of Staten Island Community College, regarding Paper on Professional Staff, September 14, 1964; Typed letter to Dr. Walter L. Willig, President of Staten Island Community College, saying he was sending 3 copies of a paper titled, "Brief Summary of Practices in the Community Colleges Relating to Professional Staff."
    - Letter from Dr. Walter L. Willig, President of Staten Island Community College, regarding Paper on Professional Staff, September 4, 1964; Typed letter from Dr. Walter L. Willig, President of Staten Island Community College, asking for a copy of a paper titled, "Brief Summary of Practices in the Community Colleges Relating the the Professional Staff."
    - Letter from Richard F. Grego, Dean of Sullivan County Community College, regarding College Chaplains, August 16, 1966; Typed letter from Richard F. Grego, Dean of Sullivan County Community College, asking Almstead to complete a questionnaire on college chaplains.
    - Letter from Ralph A. Galbraith, Dean of L.C. Smith College of Engineering at Syracuse University, regarding Industrial Engineering Curriculum Meeting, January 21, 1964; Typed letter from Ralph A. Galbraith, Dean of L.C. Smith College of Engineering at Syracuse University, regarding a conference with community colleges and Syracuse University. Conference was on SU's new industrial engineering curriculum. Included are typed minutes from the conference and list of faculty in the Department of Industrial Engineering at SU.
    - Letter from Robert S. McDowell, Assistant to the Dean of L.C. Smith College of Engineering at Syracuse University regarding former OCC Students, October 19, 1965; Typed letter from Robert S. McDowell, Assistant to the Dean of L.C. Smith College of Engineering at Syracuse University, noting 4 former OCC students now enrolled at Syracuse University's Engineering program.
    - Letter to Philip C. Martin, President of Westchester Community College, regarding filling Chemistry Technician Position, October 2, 1963; Typed letter to Phillip C. Martin, President of Westchester Community College, informing him that OCC was looking for a chemistry technician.
    - Letter from Philip C. Martin, President of Westchester Community College, regarding Chemistry Technician Position, October 29, 1963; Typed letter from Philip C. Martin, President of Westchester Community College, informing Almstead that Westchester Community College did not have a candidate for the chemistry technician position at OCC and that they were currently looking to fill that position.
    - Letter to Philip C. Martin, President of Westchester Community College, regarding Invitation to Dedication, September 16, 1964; Typed letter to Philip C. Martin, President of Westchester Community College, congratulating him on the dedication of Westchester Community College's new Physical Education building but he could not attend the dedication.
    - Letter to Philip C. Martin, President of Westchester Community College, regarding Professional Personnel Committee, July 21, 1965; Typed letter to Philip C. Martin, President of Westchester Community College, regarding report for a committee on Professional Personnel.